Okay בוקר
טוב *boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is דף ל"ט *daf lamed tes*
שבועות shvuos, *Shavuos*. We've started the פרק *perek* of שבועת הפקדון shvuat
ha-pikadon, *Shevuat HaPikadon*. Yesterday we read through the entire משנה Mishnah *mishna*,
which was the משניות *mishnayos* of all of the entire פרק *perek*,
and now we pick up at the bottom of ל"ח עמוד ב'
*lamed chet amud bais* in the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. Okay, and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks a question, not directly responding to any particular
point made in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, just to the phenomenon of
שבועת הדיינים *shevuat hadayanim*. היכי משבינן ליה? *Heichi mashbinan lei?* How do
we impose the שבועה shvuah *shevua*? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: משביעין
אותו בשבועה האמורה בתורה *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: Mashbin oso bishvua
ha'amora batorah*.
So what we do is
we
use as a model the שבועה shvuah, *shevua*, you know, that אברהם
*Avraham* made his servant make to him: דכתיב dechtiv, ואשביעך בה' אלוהי
השמים *dechesiv v'ashbiacha bashem elokei hashamayim* ואלוהי הארץ אשר לא תקח אשה
לבני מבנות הכנעני אשר אנכי יושב בקרבו *v'elokei ha'aretz asher lo sikach
isha livni mibnos hakna'ani asher anochi yoshev bekirbo*. And that's our model.
Now, okay, that's our model, but what exactly are we learning from
it? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes we're learning from it the
emphasis of בה' *bashem*. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *amar lei
Ravina leRav Ashi*, so רבינא *Ravina* said to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*:
כמאן? כרבי חנינא בר אידי דאמר בעינן שם המיוחד *Keman? KeRabbi Chanina
bar Idi de'amar ba'inan shem hameyuchad*. You only do it with, you
know, God's שם המיוחד *shem hameyuchad*, using God's direct name. אמר ליה
*Amar lei*, so is that what you're saying? אמר ליה *Amar lei*,
no, אפילו תימא רבנן דאמרי בכינוי *afilu teima rabbanan de'amri bechinuy*, even
according to the רבנן *rabbanan* that say that you can use a
different name, אל *El*, you don't have to use י-ה-ו-ה *Yud-Ke-Vav-Ke*. So
what do we mean to use this model then? ונפקא מינה צריך
לאתפוסי חפצא בידיה *V'nafka mina tzarich lehatfisei cheftza beyadei*, that you have
to hold onto some holy object in the making of a שבועה
shvuah *shevua*, like the putting of your hand on a Bible. You
have to hold onto a ספר תורה torah *sefer torah*. And that's
what we learn out from אברהם *Avraham*, because he had his servant
שים נא ידך תחת ירכי *ssim na yadecha tachas yerechi*, and the
understanding was he held to the ברית מילה *bris milah* of אברהם
*Avraham*, which was the thing that recognized like a מצווה *mitzvah* and
like the obligation to God,
and therefore that's what we learn out from it. Okay,
so גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this: וכדרבא *uk'deRava*, like רבא *Rava*,
דאמר רבא *de'amar Rava*, האי דיינא דאשבע בה' אלוהי השמים *hai dayana
de'ashba bashem elokei hashamayim* נעשה כמי שטועה בדבר משנה וחוזר *na'asa kemi
sheto'eh bidvar mishna vechozer*. If a דיין *dayan* makes somebody take a
שבועה shvuah, *shevua* and just uses the ה' אלוהי השמים *Hashem elokei
hashamayim*, it's all very cryptic here because it's like a little עיקר
חסר מן הספר *ikar chaser min hasefer*, but saying just uses the
ה' אלוהי השמים *Hashem elokei hashamayim* and doesn't demand that the person
hold onto a holy object, so you're it's as if you're טועה
בדבר משנה *to'eh bidvar mishna*. Such a well-accepted הלכה *halakha* that that
is like an inexcusable mistake. וחוזר *Vechozer*,
and therefore, you know, the דין *din* would reverse itself because that
is completely an out-of-bounds act. That gets back to discussions in סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin* about what types of things are חוזר *chozer*. ואמר רב פפא
*ve'amar Rav Pappa*, האי דיינא דאשבע בתפילין *hai dayana de'ashba betfillin* נעשה
כמי שטועה בדבר משנה וחוזר *na'asa kemi sheto'eh bidvar mishna vechozer*. Not
only that, you know, not only if you didn't use any object,
but even if you used תפילין *tfillin* but you didn't use a
ספר תורה *sefer torah*, that also would be like טועה בדבר משנה
*to'eh bidvar mishna*, and you have to use a ספר תורה *sefer
torah*. Okay, the question of course is that wasn't the case by
אברהם *Avraham*, but אברהם *Avraham* really didn't have a choice. Okay, והלכתא
כוותיה דרבא *vehilchesa kevashei deRava*, the הלכה *halakha* is like רבא *Rava*
that if you don't use any type of a holy object, it's
a complete mistake. ולא הלכתא כוותיה דרב פפא *velo hilchesa kevashei deRav
Pappa*. הלכתא כוותיה דרבא דהלא נקט חפצא בידיה *Hilchesa kevashei deRava dehalo
nakat cheftza beyadei*, because if you're not holding any holy object, it's
clearly not a good שבועה shvuah, *shevua*. ולא הלכתא כוותיה דרב פפא
דהא נקט חפצא בידיה דהלא ספר תורה *velo hilchesa kevashei deRav Pappa
deha nakat cheftza beyadei dehalo sefer torah*, that even if you're only
holding onto, you know, to תפילין *tfillin*, it's not a ספר תורה
*sefer torah*, that's still good enough. Okay. שבועה shvuah, בעומד *Shevua be'umad*,
now a שבועה shvuah, *shevua* is you have to be standing when
you take it. תלמיד חכם ביושב *Talmid chacham beyoshev*, but if you're
a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, then you can be sitting. Again, this
is a whole thing about deference to תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* in
the court system, which I can never really fully wrap my head
around. Okay. שבועה shvuah בספר תורה *Shevua besefer torah*, תלמיד חכם לכתחילה
בתפילין *talmid chacham lechatchila betfillin*. Your שבועה shvuah, *shevua* should be a
ספר תורה *sefer torah*. Okay, if you use תפילין *tfillin* it's okay,
that's what we just said. But a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, you
know, it can be with תפילין *tfillin* לכתחילה *lechatchila* you can be
with תפילין *tfillin*. Maybe the sense is that the use of the
ספר תורה *sefer torah*, these various things, making somebody stand, you know,
using a ספר תורה *sefer torah*, these are things that are to
like impose the fear and the awe of what a שבועה shvuah
*shevua* means and what a false שבועה shvuah, *shevua* would mean. And
if somebody is a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, they don't need that
same degree of drama. So תפילין *tfillin* is good enough for the
requirement of a holy object, but maybe it's not as fear-inducing, you
know, as a ספר תורה *sefer torah*. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabbanan*, שבועת
הדיינים אף היא בלשונם נאמרה *shevuat hadayanim af hi bilshonam ne'emra*. So
this is in from סוטה Sotah. *Sota* in תוספתא *Tosefta* where it
says all the things that could be said that need דווקא *dafka*
Hebrew and then all things that could be said in any translation.
So it says שבועת הדיינים *shevuat hadayanim* can be said in any
language. Okay. אומרים לו omrim lo, *Omrim lo*, you say to him:
הוי יודע hevei yodeia, *hevei yodea*, be aware, שכל העולם כולו נזדעזע
בשעה שאמר הקדוש ברוך הוא בסיני *shekol ha'olam kulo nizdazeia besha'a she'amar
hakadosh baruch hu beSinai*. So here we're trying to instill the fear
and the awe so that the person doesn't swear falsely. Okay.
And so you should know that the whole world trembled when God
said לא תשא את שם ה׳ אלקיך לשוא. lo tisa et shem
hashem elohecha lashav. Why? Because it says ולא ינקה ה׳ את אשר
ישא שמו לשוא. velo yenake hashem et asher yisa shemo lashav. So
you should realize how enormous this would be if you were to
take a false oath. וכל עבירות שבתורה נאמר בהן ונקה, vechol aveirot
shebatorah neemar bahen venake, all the other sins it says God will
cleanse. וכאן נאמר לא ינקה, vekahn neemar lo yenake, כי לא ינקה
ה׳ את אשר ישא שמו לשוא. ki lo yenake hashem et asher
yisa shemo lashav. Everything else it says נקה לא ינקה, nake lo
yenake, which we read the פשט pshat is doesn't fully cleanse, we
read it נקה לשבים ולא ינקה לאינה שבים, nake lashavim velo yenake
le'eina shavim, but there's a נקה nake at least. But by שבועת
שוא, shvuat shav, God will never, לא ינקה, lo yenake, כי לא
ינקה. ki lo yenake. וכל עבירות שבתורה נפרעים ממנו, vechol aveirot shebatorah
nifra'im mimenu,
all sins, you're the one that gets punished, the sinner. וכאן ממנו
וממשפחתו, vekahn mimenu umimishpachto, it's also your family that's going to get
punished. שנאמר, shenemar, אל תתן את פיך לחטיא את בשרך, al titein
et picha lachati et besarecha, do not allow your mouth to bring
sin upon your flesh, meaning your family, because of taking a false
oath. ואין בשר אלא קרובו, ve'ein basar ela kerovo, your flesh means
your relative. שנאמר, shenemar, ומבשרך לא תתעלם, umibesarcha lo titalem,
do not hide away from those that are from your very own
flesh. וכל עבירות שבתורה נפרעים ממנו וכאן ממנו ומכל העולם, vechol aveirot
shebatorah nifra'im mimenu vekahn mimenu umikol haolam, all sins, it's just you;
here, not only is it your family, it's actually the whole world
suffers. That's the whole world trembled, לא תשא lo sisa. את שם
ה׳ אלקיך לשוא. What are we doing with God's name, the very
trust that we're doing in God, we're violating it, that we call
God to witness and then we're doing something false. שנאמר, shenemar, אלה
וכחש, alah vechachesh,
an oath and denial and the rest of this פסוק pasuk
is
really what it's going on. Here's what the פסוק pasuk reads, this
is הושע ד ב. Hoshea daled bet. אלה וכחש ורצוח וגנוב ונאוף,
alah vechachesh veratzoach veganov vena'of, a false swearing, dishonesty, denial, and murder,
and burglary and adultery,
פרצו, paratzu, have burst forth, are widespread in the land. ודמים בדמים
נגעו, udamim bedamim naga'u, and blood has touched upon blood. על כן
תאבל הארץ, al ken te'evel ha'aretz, therefore the land will mourn. ואומלל
כל יושב בה, ve'umlal kol yoshev bah, and will be bereaved, all
that dwell in the land. בחיית השדה ובעוף השמים וגם דגי הים
יאספו. bechayat hasadeh uve'of hashamayim vegam degei hayam ye'aseifu. So the entire
world is being affected by this. Now that's a whole litany of
sins, but starts with the oath. Okay.
So that's the whole world. So then the גמרא gemara says, ואימא
עד דעביד לכולהו, ve'eima ad de'avid lekulhu, maybe only if you do
all of the sins mentioned? לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka datach, it
doesn't make sense. דכתיב, it says in a completely different פסוק pasuk
in ירמיה, Yirmiyah, מפני
אלה
אבלה הארץ,
mipnei alah
avelah ha'aretz,
because of the oath the land is mourning. וכתיב, vechtiv, and it
says back in הושע, Hoshea, על כן תאבל הארץ ואומלל כל יושב
בה. al ken te'evel ha'aretz ve'umlal kol yoshev bah. So you sort
of the exact same phrase using, and in the end, what's drawn
a line under is the false oath. וכל עבירות שבתורה אם יש
לו זכות תולים לו שנים ושלשה דורות, vechol aveirot shebatorah im yesh
lo zechut tolim lo shnayim ushlosha dorot, all other sins, if you
have merit, then the punishment is held back two or three generations.
וכאן נפרעים ממנו לאלתר, vekahn nifra'im mimenu le'altar,
here it's immediate. שנאמר, shenemar, הוצאתיה נאם ה׳ צבאות ובאה אל בית
הגנב ואל בית הנשבע בשמי לשקר, hotzeitia neum hashem tzevaot uvah el
beit haganav ve'el beit hanishba bishmi lashaker, I will eject him, says
God, and it'll come to the house of the גנב ganav and
the house of one who takes my oath falsely. ולנה בתוך ביתו
וכלתו ואת עציו ואת
אבניו, velanah betoch beito vechilat'o ve'et etzav ve'et avanav, the sin will
destroy him and the wood and the stones. הוצאתיה, hotzeitia, I will
reject, kick him out. לאלתר, le'altar, immediately. ובאה אל בית הגנב, uvah
el beit haganav, it comes to the house of the one who
burglarizes. זה גונב דעת הבריות, ze gonev da'at habriyot,
this is the one who deceives his friends or makes it seem
like he, גניבת
דעת gneivat da'at sometimes is that you make somebody think that you're
extending an invitation or that you're doing something nice for them when
really that was never really your plan. You wanted them to be
indebted to you but you never really were offering them what you
were offering them. That's a classic example of גניבת דעת. gneivat da'at.
Here גניבת דעת gneivat da'at is used very much in the sense
of just misrepresenting and here it's דוקא davka in order to, for
financial gain. Okay.
So you demand that somebody, you say you owe me a hundred
dollars and the person doesn't know, I don't know if I do,
whatever, and you make him take a שבועה shvuah, and in the
end, you're making it all up and in order to avoid a
שבועה, shvuah, he's going to pay you. ואל בית הנשבע בשמי לשקר,
ve'el beit hanishba bishmi lashaker, to the house of one who takes
my name falsely. כמשמעו, kemashma'o, like it says. ולנה בתוך ביתו וכלתו
ואת עציו ואת אבניו, velanah betoch beito vechilat'o ve'et etzav ve'et avanav,
הלמדת, halamadeta, דברים שאין אש אוכלתן שבועת שקר מכלה אותן, devarim she'ein
esh ochaltan shvuat sheker mechala otan, things that fire can't consume, a
false oath will consume them. things that even fire and water cannot
destroy, like you know, the stones, שבועת שקר מכלה אותם, shvuat shaker
mechalosam, this false oath comes and it, you know, the sin, the
false oath comes, dwells in the house and destroys the entire house.
אם אומר איני נשבע, im omer eini nishba, so you give him
all of these, you put the fear of God into him. Okay,
אם אומר, im omer, if the guy says איני נשבע, eini nishba,
I won't take an oath, פוטרין אותו מיד, potrin oso mi-yad, you
immediately say, fine, goodbye. Okay, no oath, pay up, and you try
to, like, move it on so that he does not reverse himself
and retract himself.
There's a whole question in רש"י ותוספות, Rashi ve-Tosafos, is he allowed
to retract himself? But you know, it might be that even if
he is allowed, you try to sort of wrap it up quickly
so he doesn't.
ואם אמר הריני נשבע, ve-im amar ha-reini nishba, says I get all
of that and still I'm going to take the oath. So העומדים
שם אומרים זה לזה, ha-omdim sham omrim zeh la-zeh, those that are
standing say one to another, סורו נא מעל אהלי האנשים הרשעים האלה,
suru na me-al ohalei ha-anashim ha-reshaim ha-eleh, turn away from these, the
tent of these evil people. So it actually says that the person
who makes him take a שבועה shvuah is also evil, like the
whole idea of taking a שבועה, even if it might be truthful,
you know, like clearly there's like it would, it's terrible to take
a שבועה, which is why there's been long-standing practice, you know, that
Jews don't take שבועות, shvuos נדרים nedarim maybe, but like even a
שבועת אמת, shvuat emes, you know, the idea of like the consequence
of a possible false שבועה, you know, is just so enormous. So
here when the guy's taking a שבועה, it's like everybody's con-, like
both the person who makes you take the שבועה and you, you're
all רשעים, reshaim, like we got to just keep our distance from
this. Pretty harsh. וכשמשביעין אותו, u-kse-mashbi-in oso, when you have him take
the שבועה, אומרים לו, you say to him, הוי יודע, hevei yodeia,
and the גמרא's gemara going to unpack this entire ברייתא. braisa. הוי
יודע, be aware, שלא על דעתך אנו משביעין אותך, she-lo al datcha
anu mashbi-in oscha, not what you say the words mean, אלא על
דעת המקום ועל דעת בית דין, ela al da'as ha-Makom ve-al da'as
Beis Din, but on what God means, you know, sort of thinks
and what we're thinking. So, you know, there are ways people could
make a trick and say something that sounds like one thing and
technically it's true, but you know, really they have in mind something
totally different. The גמרא gemara will discuss that. So,
you know, like, like אנכי עשיו בכורך Anochi Eisav bechorecha or something
like that. So it's not what you think you mean by these
words, it's what we are assuming the words that you're saying mean.
שכן מצינו במשה רבינו, she-ken matzinu be-Moshe Rabbeinu, this is what we
found by Moshe,
כשמשביע ישראל, ke-she-mashbi-a Yisrael, when he made Yisrael take the oath, you
know, by ערבות מואב, Arvos Moav,
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said, דעו שלא על דעתכם אני משביע
אתכם, de'u she-lo al datchaschem ani mashbi-a eschem, not if you have
some thought in your mouth, like you have you're crossing your your
fingers behind your back, or, you know, you're trying to in your
head saying qualifying it, not what's going through your mind and you
want the words to mean, אלא על דעת המקום ועל דעתי, ela
al da'as ha-Makom ve-al da'asi, but on mine, you know, what God
intends and what I intend. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, ולא אתכם לבדכם, ve-lo itchem
levadchem, you know, אנכי כורת את הברית הזאת, anochi koreis es ha-bris
ha-zos, כי את
אשר ישנו פה. ki es asher yeshno poh. Now, it's not exactly
clear how that proves it, but it seems like it's saying ולא
אתכם, ve-lo itchem, not with you, not what you're thinking and you're
going to say you mean by these words, no, it's what we're
saying these words mean. And now we're continuing to דרשן darshan it,
כי את אשר ישנו פה, ki es asher yeshno poh, אין לי
אלא אותן העומדים על הר סיני, ein li ela osan ha-omdim al
Har Sinai, that's only those that were standing on Har Sinai. Actually
then it was ערבות מואב Arvos Moav not Har Sinai. דורות הבאים
וגרים העתידים להתגייר מנין? doros ha-ba'im ve-gerim ha-asidim le-hisgayer minayin? So this
is the whole idea that everybody was at Har Sinai. How do
I know it includes all future generations? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, ואת
אשר איננו, ve-es asher eineno, even those that are not here. ואין
לי
אלא מצות שקיבלו עליהם מהר סיני, ve-ein li ela mitzvos she-kiblu aleihem
me-Har Sinai, and that's only the mitzvos that were like there at
the time of the מדבר, midbar, Har Sinai, ערבות מואב. Arvos Moav.
מנין מצות העתידות להתחדש כגון מקרא מגילה מנין? minayin mitzvos ha-asidos le-his-chadesh
kegon mikra megilla minayin? How do I know that the concept of
קבלת מצוות, kabbalas mitzvos, you know, that everybody was taking they were
entering into this שבועה included even future things that would be like
like מקרא מגילה, mikra megilla, other מצוות mitzvos that would come up?
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, קימו וקבלו, kimu ve-kiblu, קימו מה שקיבלו כבר.
kimu mah she-kiblu kvar. Okay, at the time of מגילה megilla they
accepted and there it was it wasn't Har Sinai and they were
just sort of accepting even God's presence even when it's more hidden
and their obligation to תורה ומצוות Torah u-mitzvos and so on.
Where are we? מאי אף היא בלשון נאמרה? mai af hi bi-leshon
ne-emrah? Okay, so that's the whole ברייתא, braisa, very long ברייתא. braisa.
Now we're going to unpack it. מאי אף היא בלשון נאמרה, mai
af hi bi-leshon ne-emrah, what does it mean even if it can
be said in its
language? כדתנן, ki-de-snan, it's in conversation with the משנה in סוטה. אלו
נאמרין בכל לשון, elu ne-emrin be-chol lashon, the following can be said
in any language: פרשת סוטה, parshas Sotah, וידוי מעשר, viduy ma'aser, the
parsha of Sotah, you know,
that when you make her take the שבועה, you know, that that
she did not sleep with any man. I mean, you write it
on a קלף klaf in Hebrew, but you make her take the
שבועה, you know, could be in any language.
And the וידוי מעשר viduy ma'aser when you every three years, you
know, you say that you've done everything you're supposed to do with
the מעשר. ma'aser. קריאת שמע ותפילה, krias shema u-tefilla, Krias Shema and
שמונה עשרה, shmoneh esrei, וברכת המזון, u-virchas ha-mazon, bentching, ושבועת העדות, u-shvuas
ha-eidus, now we're getting to the שבועות we talked about. Okay, ושבועת
הפקדון. u-shvuas ha-pikadon. Okay, so the משנה said שבועת עדות shvuat eidus
and שבועת הפקדון, it didn't mention
שבועת הדיינין. shvuat ha-dayanin. ותניא נמי הכי. ve-sanya nami hachi. אמר מר
אמרו לו, amar mar amru lo, you say to them הוי יודע
שכל העולם כולו נזדעזע בשעה שאמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לא תשא את
שם ה' אלהיך לשוא. havei yodea she'kol ha'olam kulo nizdaze'a besha'ah she'amar
hakadosh baruch hu lo sisa es shem Hashem elokecha lashav. The entire
world trembled. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אילימא משום דאיתיהיב בסיני, eilima mishum
de'isyehiv b'Sinai, because it was given at Har Sinai? So everybody was
trembling at Har Sinai. So עשרת הדברות נמי איזדעזע, Aseres hadibros nami
izdaze'a, so the whole Ten Commandments. ואלא משום דחמירא, ve'ela mishum de'chamira,
okay because it's very strict. ומי חמירא, umi chamira, how strict is
it? והתנן אלו הן הקלות, vehatnan elu hen hakalos, the following are
the lighter עבירות: aveiros: עשה ולא תעשה חוץ מלא תשא. aseh v'lo
sa'aseh chutz mi'lo sisa. All positive and negative commandments except for לא
תשא. lo sisa. וחמורות, v'hachamuros, the weightier ones are זו כריתות ומיתות
בית דין ולא תשא עמהם. zu krisos u'misos beis din v'lo sisa
imahem. Things חייב כרת, chayav kares, things חייב מיתת בית דין chayav
misas beis din and לא תשא. So לא תשא את שם ה'
אלהיך לשוא lo sisa es shem Hashem elokecha lashav is certainly weightier
than a normal לא תעשה, lo sa'aseh, even though there's no כרת
kares or מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. But it's not more
weighty than כרת kares and מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. So
what do you mean that the whole world trembled? There's plenty of
things that are כרת kares and מיתת בית דין. misas beis din.
This isn't weightier than that. אלא כדקתני טעמא, ela k'diksani ta'ama,
fine, the reason the world trembled is for what the ברייתא braisa
says in the next sentence: שבכל עבירות שבתורה נאמר ונקה וכאן נאמר
לא ינקה, she'bechol aveiros she'batorah ne'emar v'nakeh v'kan ne'emar lo yenakeh,
because you can never be forgiven for it. So it's true, it's
not weightier than כרת kares and מיתת בית דין, misas beis din,
but the reason people trembled is because it's like you ain't coming
back from it. There's no way you can get כפרה kaparah for
it. שבכל עבירות שבתורה לא
נאמר בהן לא ינקה, she'bechol aveiros she'batorah lo ne'emar bahen lo yenakeh,
is that really true? והכתיב ונקה לא ינקה? v'haksiv v'nakeh lo yenakeh?
ונקה לא ינקה, v'nakeh lo yenakeh, it says לא ינקה. lo yenakeh.
So the גמרא gemara says no, ההוא מבעי ליה לכדרבי אלעזר, hahu
mibaye leh l'chiderabbi Elazar, which anyway ונקה לא ינקה v'nakeh lo yenakeh
means like does not fully forgive. It doesn't just stam say לא
ינקה. lo yenakeh. But anyway the גמרא says no, ההוא מבעי ליה
לכדרבי אלעזר, hahu mibaye leh l'chiderabbi Elazar, דתניא ר' אלעזר אומר, detanya
Rabbi Elazar omer, אי אפשר לומר ונקה, ee efshar lomar v'nakeh, you
can't say that God totally cleanses, שכבר נאמר לא ינקה. she'kvar ne'emar
lo yenakeh. אי אפשר לומר לא ינקה, ee efshar lomar lo yenakeh,
you can't say God doesn't cleanse, שכבר נאמר ונקה. she'kvar ne'emar v'nakeh.
הא כיצד? ha keitzad? מנקה הוא לשבים ואינו מנקה לשאינם שבים. menakeh
hu lashavim v'eino menakeh leshainam shavim.
God, you know, forgiveness for those who do תשובה, teshuva, but not
for those who don't do תשובה. teshuva. Okay, that's the classic interpretation.
Let's just read one more. שבכל עבירות
שבתורה נפרעין הימנו וכאן הימנו וממשפחתו. she'bechol aveiros she'batorah nifra'in heimenu v'kan
heimenu u'mimishpachto. In all other עבירות aveiros it's from him, and here
from him and his family. So the גמרא says שבכל עבירות שבתורה
ממשפחתו לא? she'bechol aveiros she'batorah mimishpachto lo? You're telling me that in
other sins the family also doesn't get it? This is a general
issue. You know the תורה says איש בחטאו יומתו, ish b'cheto yumasu,
and then there's also about other things that indicate that sometimes it's
not just individual, that there are those in the family, you know,
later generations or the family itself that also suffers. והא כתיב ושמתי
אני את פני באיש ההוא ובמשפחתו, v'ha ksiv v'samti ani es panai
ba'ish hahu u'v'mishpachto, I will set my face against that man and
his family. This is by עבודה זרה avodah zarah or giving the
child to מולך. molech. דתניא אמר רבי שמעון אם הוא חטא משפחתו
מה חטאת? detanya amar Rabbi Shimon im hu chata mishpachto mah chatas?
If he sinned what did the family sin? לומר לך אין לך
משפחה שיש בה מוכס שאין כולם מוכסים. lomar lach ein lach mishpacha
sheyesh bah mochs she'ein kulam mochsin. There's no family that has a
tax
collector that, you know, the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, the head of
the household doesn't have everybody party to his evil
doings. People are making excuses for him, actively helping him out, silently
supporting him. Now the question about what exact choice do they always
have and so on is an interesting one but okay. So here
we're saying not it's not just stam your family is being punished
and they're totally innocent, but it's seen that your family is sort
of is also to some
degree part of your sin. So now does that mean that's always
true? Is that only for certain types of sins? Okay, that's not
clear. But anyway, it's not that this is the only sin, the
שבועה, that the family is punished. So the גמרא says והכי קאמר
אין לך
משפחה שיש בה ליסטין שאין כולם ליסטין,
v'hachi ka'amar ein
lach mishpacha sheyesh bah listin she'ein kulam listin, and there's no family
that, you know, has a bandit man that not everybody is somehow
a bandit man as well. מפני שמחפים עליו, mipnei shemechaphin alav, because
they cover up for him. So you see that other sins also
the family? So the גמרא says התם בדינא אחרינא הכא בדינא דידיה.
hasam b'dina achrina hacha b'dina didei. No, there they're punished in a,
you know, a lesser punishment. You know, they're accessories.
Here the
family is given the same punishment. Now does that mean even if
the family is not assisting, or only when they are
assisting? Not clear. But either way we're saying that by שבועה it's
the same punishment, not just a lesser one.
דתניא רבי אומר והכרתי אותו. detanya Rebbe omer v'hikrasti oso. מה תלמוד
לומר? mah talmud lomar? And but I will destroy him from the
midst of his people, that's back to the פסוק pasuk of משפחתו.
mishpachto. לפי שנאמר ושמתי אני את פני באיש ההוא ובמשפחתו, lefi she'ne'emar
v'samti ani es panai ba'ish hahu u'v'mishpachto, יכול כל המשפחה כולה בהכרת,
yachol kol hamishpacha kulo b'hares, maybe even the whole family gets כרת?
kares? תלמוד לומר אותו. talmud lomar oso. אותו בהכרת ולא כל המשפחה
כולה. oso b'hares v'lo kol hamishpacha kulo. Him with כרת kares and
not the whole family. אותו בכרת ולא כל המשפחה כולה בכרת. Oso
b'kares v'lo kol hamishpacha kulah b'kares. Okay, he gets כרת Kares but
not the whole family, so in other עבירות Aveiros the family gets
like only as accessories and here the family gets the full whammy.
So we will end for here for now, pick up here tomorrow.